Guide to the Ithaca movie industry photograph collection, 1915-1965.
Ithaca movie industry photograph collection
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Ithaca movie industry photograph collection, 1915-1965.
2959
Hennessy, Mame,
.3 cubic ft.
Photographs
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Photographs of movie actors and actresses, movie sets in Ithaca, New York, scenes from movies and various public events in Ithaca.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Ithaca, New York was a silent film center from 1910 through the 1920s. The Wharton Brothers Studio was located in Renwick (now Stewart) Park.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Photographs of movie actors and actresses, movie sets in Ithaca, New York, scenes from movies and various public events in Ithaca, collected by actress Mame (Mary L.) Hennessy. Also, personal photographs of Mary Hennessy, her family, friends and residences; letters and postcards, 1917-1964; news clippings, 1917, 1949-1961; miscellaneous manuscript and printed material, 1947-1965; and photographic negatives. Includes photographs of Irene Castle, Grace Darling, Doris Kenyon, Derwent Hall Caine, Florence Short, Marguerrete Marsh, Lillian Walker, Betty Howe, Frances White, Pearl White, Jean Sothern, Elsie Baker, Evelyn Ferris, Dick Steward, Eddie Kaw, E. Coit Albertson, and Creighton Hale.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Hennessy, Mame,; Albertson, E. Coit.; Baker, Elsie.; Caine, Derwent Hall.; Castle, Irene, 1893-1969.; Darling, Grace, 1893-1963.; Farris, Evelyn.; Hale, Creighton.; Hennessy, Mary L.; Howe, Betty.; Kaw, Eddie.; Kenyon, Doris.; Marsh, Marguerrete.; Sothern, Jean.; Stewart, Dick.; Walker, Lillian.; White, Frances.; White, Pearl, 1889-1938.; Wharton Studio (Ithaca, N.Y.)
Subjects:
Motion picture actors and actresses.; Motion picture studios -- New York (State) -- Ithaca.; Women in the motion picture industry.
Places:
Ithaca (N.Y.); Tompkins County (N.Y.)
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Photographs
Subseries Ia. Still Photographs of Actors and Actresses
Subseries Ib. Movie Sets, Lots, and Shooting
Subseries Ic. Scenes from Movies Pre-1928
Subseries Id. Various Public Events in Ithaca
Subseries Ie. Personal Photographs
Series II. Letters and Postcards
Series III. Miscellaneous Printed Material
Series IV. News Clippings
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Photographs (Box 1)
  - Subseries Ia. Still Photographs of Actors and Actresses
    - Mary Hennessy in Spanish riding costume, A1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Mary Hennessy in fur coat for "The Great White Trail.", A2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Mary Hennessy, with hair down, sitting on a beach, A3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Mary Hennessy, with hair down, sitting on beach. Different than above shot, A4 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Mary Hennessy, with hair down, passport style photographs (14 photographs, different poses), ca. 1920s; A5 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Irene Castle, with famous Castle "bob" and pearls, A6 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Irene Castle, costumed in military uniform, A7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Irene Castle in satin gown with ostrich feather fan. Autographed, A8 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Grace Darling, head and shoulders. Autographed, A9 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Grace Darling, seated on rock face, A10 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Doris Kenyon, with tulle veil. Autographed, A11 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Florence Short, black lace dress. Autographed, A12 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Florence Short, black lace dress. Different from above., A13 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Marguerrete [sic] Marsh, head and shoulders. Autographed, A14 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Lillian Walker, with parrot. Autographed, A15 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Betty Howe, with flower (copy), A16 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Betty Howe seated on a table against a mirror. Autographed, A17 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Frances White, with long ringlets. Autographed, A18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Pearl White, head and shoulders, in "Hazel K", A19 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Pearl White, reclining on a stone bench, A20 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Jean Sothern, on a tree trunk with a cat. Autographed, A21 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Elsie Baker in velvet gown with buttoned boots. Autographed, March 30, 1916; A22 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Elsie Baker head and shoulders with fur neck piece, A23 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Evelyn Ferris leaning against tree trunk. Autographed, A24 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Muro", a young woman in Japanese Costume, A25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified Ithaca girl trying out. Diaphanous white shawl and dress against background of willow trees, A26 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified star, head and shoulders, pearls around neck. De Barron Studios, NYC, A27 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Same star as above, with pearls around neck. De Barron Studios, NYC, A28 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Derwent Hall Caine, arms folded. Autographed, A29 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Creighton Hale, head and shoulders, arms folded, A30 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - E. Coit Albertson costumed for "Million Dollar Mystery." Autographed, A31 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Eddie Kaw head and shoulders, arms folded. Autographed, A32 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Dick Steward, costumed for "The Circus." Autographed, A33 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Dick Steward in cowboy costume, A34 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Pearl White, head and shoulders with fox neck piece, A35 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified man with mustache in Western Costume, A36 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified man in headgear with triangular piece over forehead, A37 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified girl in Hawaiian costume with straw skirt, A38 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified girl with flowers in her hair, sitting pose, A39 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Subseries Ib. Movie Sets, Lots, and Shooting
    - Group of people outside casting office, B1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Shows photographer (US Flag and tents in the background), B2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Interior with man holding numbers in foreground (shot sequence?), B3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Airplane with Jim Gordon, Leo Wharton, and other men. Sign in background reads "Wharton-Inc. Ithaca, NY.", 1915-1916; B4 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Wharton-Inc. movie lot viewed from lake, B5 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Subseries Ic. Scenes from Movies Pre-1928
    - Mary Hennessy and others in scenes from the "Great White Trail", C1-C6 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Doris Kenyon, Paul Gordon, Harvey Davenport in the "Great White Trail", C7 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Mary Hennessy, Louise Hotaling, Dick Stewart in the "Great White Trail", C8 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Mary Hennessy and others in the "Great White Trail", C9-C10 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Irene Castle costumed for "Patria", C11 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Irene Castle dancing in "Patria," with Bob Causer, Pat Hennessy, Hazel Marion, Lena Keigan, Mrs. James Ward and Bernard Randall, C12 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bess Emerich (Mrs. Leo Wharton), King Baggott, Margaret Campbell. Scene from "The Eagle's Eye", C13 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Irene Castle and Milton Sills in "Patria." Taken in Ithaca gorge, likely Cascadilla, C14 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bess Emerich and Dick Stewart in "Patria", C15 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Irene Castle and Mary Hennessy in "Patria", C16 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Unidentified actors and actresses, probably in a scene from "Patria" with Warner Oland, Irene Castle and others, C17 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Matt Schiltz, Major Bill Guderman, and others at Mr. Moxon's Feed Store in "The Adventures of Wallingford", C18 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - George Homill, Maurice Bond, Pat Hennessy, all of Ithaca, in "Adventures of Wallingford", 1915; C19 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Howard Teachout, Frances White, Lolita Robertson, and Max Figman with Burr McIntosh in "Get Rich Quick" ("Adventures of Wallingford"), C20 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Mary Hennessy and Margie Reulin with others unidentified in Wallingford Series, C21 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Mary Hennessy, Mrs. Reulin, Hazel Marion, Mrs J Ward, Helen Buck in Wallingford Series, C22 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Burr McIntosh in "The Adventures of Wallingford", C23 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Early plane with pilot rescuing woman from the water, C24 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Woman in washtub, policeman and a dog in someone's garden. 2 shots, C25-C26 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Court room scene with Jim and Pat Hennessy, Dick Stewart, Lou Oliver, Dan Crowley and others. 2 copies, C27 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Mary Hennessy with two unidentified women on a settee, C28 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Harry Fox and Ithaca policemen in "Beatrice Fairfax" series, C29 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bill Bracken, Marguerite Marsh, Carylyn Marbo, Precious Personius--warden, in "The Million Dollar Mystery", C30 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Dale Gass, Clarence Smith, George Connor, Ralph Durphy, Harry Fox, Berry. 2 copies, C31 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Motor launch on a lake, C32 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Mary Hennessy, Edith Tree, Hazel Marion, Babe Cole in restaurant scene, C33 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Mary Hennessy and Lillian Walker, 1915; C34 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Mary Hennessy, Lillian Walker, Billy Pike, 1915; C35 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Billy Pike and Lillian Walker, 1915; C36 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Mary Hennessy and Lillian Walker, C37 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Unidentified man and woman with Saint Bernard dog, C38 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Mary Hennessy with unidentified man and woman in doorway, C39 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Mary Hennessy with same man and woman as above, but with three other people, C40 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Mary Hennessy about to use the telephone, C41 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Mary Hennessy telephoning, C42 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Howard Teachout, Mary Hennessy, Max Figman in "Get Rich Quick", C43 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Unidentified actors and actresses, C44-45 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Ariel and Norma Bement, George Homill, Maurice Bond, Harold Urband, 1915-1916; C46 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Grace Darling and others outside a hotel, C47 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Grace Darling and others, including man with rifle and a man holding a bucket and a rope, C48 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Unidentified group of people standing on the grass outside a hotel, C49 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Subseries Id. Various Public Events in Ithaca, 1940s-1950s
    - Mary Hennessy, Hostess at Warren Hall, CU, October 25, 1946; D1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Rally. Sue Roosevelt, Franklin D. Roosevelt Jr., Mary Hennessy, Daniel Crowley, Katie Crowley, October 16, 1954; D2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Unidentified banquet with Mary Hennessy, D3-D4 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Old Time Minstrel Show, Immaculate Conception Church, April 1942; D5 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Hennessy at back of auditorium during production, D6 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Women's dinner, Hennessy in background, D7-D9 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Unidentified group of people, apparently at a costume ball. Personius, Elmire, photographer, D10 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Backstage preparations, Toby Clarey, applying makeup for amateur production, presumably Community Players. Two copies, D11 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Mary Hennessy and Bess, April 4, 1953; D12 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Amateur production, girl dressed as majorette, D13 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Ithaca Theatre--"The Playboy of the Western World", D14 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Old Ithaca College Theatre, D15-D16 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Unidentified scene from production of an operetta, D17 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Subseries Ie. Personal Photographs
    - Photographs featuring children. 10 items, n.d., 1946, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Mary Hennessy with others. 79 items, 1940s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Snapshots of residences: 319 E. Court Street, Coral Gables, Unidentified houses (most likely in Florida). 6 items. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Group shots without Mary Hennessy. 62 items. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Mary Hennessy alone. 18 items (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous. 14 items (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous negatives. 21 items, I (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series II. Letters and Postcards
  - Postcards to JJH from "Dick" from Mexico, Texas, Louisiana, Georgia, NYC. 6 items, 1917; F-1-6 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Postcard from Mame to J Hennessy, on location at Saranac Lake for "The Great White Trail", 1917; F-7 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Sympathy acknowledgement card and note from Irene Castle after husbands death in aviation accident. 2 items, February 15, 1918; F8 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letter from Bess Harris complaining of lack of mention of herself and small group for work they did in Ithaca, July 27, 1989; F9 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letter from Arch Merrill, author of newspaper articles, 1950; F10 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letter from Robert E. Treman thanking Mame for being hostess at Democratic Dinner at Ithaca Hotel, October 1, 1952; F11 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Mimeo. letter and coupon stub from Community Players, 1952-1953; F12 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letter from James Farley, enclosing picture of him and grandson with Pope Paul VI, April 17, 1964; F13 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series III. Miscellaneous Printed Material
  - "The Cornell Widow", December 1947; G1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "The Cornell Widow", May 1949; G2 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Program, "Hats Off! to Theatre in Ithaca", Statler Club, May 4, 1952; G3 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Advertisement on WHCU; Mary used as example of mother for fur gift from Louis Herman's, May 8, 1952; G4 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Letter to the Editor" by Charles Chatfield, WHCU, July 9, 1952; G5 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Copy of term paper done with help of interview from Mame, "The Development of the Motion Picture Industry in Ithaca, NY" by Charlotte White, December 17, 1960; G6 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Program for Citizenship Award Dinner, VFW. Daniel Crowley guest of honor, April 3, 1965; G7 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Script of play "Prim and Promiscuous", probably for benefit of Policemen's Ball. Spoof on "Pride and Prejudice.", G8 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series IV. News Clippings
  - Elmira Paper, death of Dennis Crowley, January 1917; H1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Ithaca Journal", July 26, 1949; H2 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Ithaca Journal", August 12, 1949; H3 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Elmira Sunday Telegram", August 20, 1950; H4 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Elmira Sunday Telegram", August 21, 1950; H5 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Ithaca Journal" local democrats, May 28, 1953; H6 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ithaca paper, with Janet O'Daniel, May 9, 1961; H7 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bake sale for democrats, 2 copies. Ithaca and Syracuse papers, H8 (Box 1, Folder 11)